<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The pollution of vniversite-learning or sciences (falsly so called) whereby most of the youth are so infected, and both they and their parents so deceived, that when they come to age, they prove either unprofitable or hurtfull members to the common-wealth ... / by that faithfull martyr of Iesus Christ, Mr. Henry Barrow ...</title>
            <author>Barrow, Henry, 1550?-1593.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B922</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18358</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11744275</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11744275</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48528</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31052)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48528)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 10:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The pollution of vniversite-learning or sciences (falsly so called) whereby most of the youth are so infected, and both they and their parents so deceived, that when they come to age, they prove either unprofitable or hurtfull members to the common-wealth ... / by that faithfull martyr of Iesus Christ, Mr. Henry Barrow ...</title>
                  <author>Barrow, Henry, 1550?-1593.</author>
                  <author>Barrow, Henry, 1550?-1593. Plain refutation of M. Giffard's booke.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Extracted from: A plaine refutation of M. Giffard's booke / H. Barrow. [London?], 1605.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gifford, George, d. 1620. --  Short treatise against the Donatists of England whome we call Brownists.</term>
               <term>Education, Higher --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48528:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48528:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE POLLUTION OF Vniverſitie-Learning, OR, SCIENCES (<hi>Falſly ſo called</hi>)</p>
            <p>Whereby moſt of the <hi>youth</hi> are ſo infected, and both they and their Parents ſo deceived, that when they come to age, they prove either unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable or hurtfull Members to the Common-wealth, as now in theſe dangerous dayes all the truly godly have dolefull exeperience; As it was well obſerved almoſt threeſcore yeers agoe, by that faithfull <hi>Martyr</hi> of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Henry Barrow,</hi> in divers of his Bookes for Separate or inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent <hi>CHVRCHES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The evill of which kinde of learning ſo attained, with many others flowing from thence, may be remedied henceforth by the grave determination of the King and Parliament.</p>
            <p>Read 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.20, 21. and <hi>Colloſſ.</hi> 1.2, 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the yeare, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:48528:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48528:2"/>
            <head>The Preface to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F thou that readeſt this Treatiſe, be one that haſt drunken of thoſe pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted Fountaines of Vniverſtie learning, which (upon the termes thou diddeſt believe it) is ſo much the more poyſonable for the ſoule, then the waters of <hi>Mara</hi> were bitter for the body, as the ſoule is more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent then the body, yet if thou haſt any true deſire (though never ſo ſmall) to be refreſhed with the cleare and freſh waters of life; or if thou wilt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waite at the Poole of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> untill the Angell of the Covenant come and cure thee, ſurely there is a poſsibility of thy recovery, and God that ſeparated light from dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, can eaſily make a ſeparation betweene the evill thou haſt received there, in thy tender yeers, and the good thou haſt attained otherwiſe; even as he did both in <hi>Moſes</hi> when he was pleaſed to call and fit him for his ſpeciall ſervice being trained up in all the wiſedome as well as the profits and pleaſures of <hi>Egypt;</hi> and alſo in <hi>Paul,</hi> who was brought up at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> and could ſpeake more languages then all the Philoſophers of <hi>Corinth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or if thou be one that baſt been taught in all godly learning (which truely both deſerveth and getteth the name in Gods Word) as the ſonnes of the Prophets were of old, and wherein <hi>Timothy</hi> was brought up from a childe, though thou be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of all Vniverſitie learning (eſpecially upon ſuch hard, or rather intolerable termes as whereby it is obtained) ſurely thou haſt great cauſe to reſt contented, uſe it to the right end, and praiſe the wiſe God, who knoweth beſt what is for thy good.</p>
            <p>And as for the tongues, which God gave at the firſt for a curſe or judgement, to binder the building of the Tower of <hi>Babel,</hi> the ſame God that can bring good out of evill, did at the firſt preaching of the Goſpel, change that curſe or judgement into a bleſsing or mercie to all Nations, through the divulging thereof to each Nation in their owne language; if theſe (I ſay) or any godly learning may be had in a holy way, doubtleſſe a happy and ſanctified uſe may be made thereof, to the glory of God and good of his Church, but no otherwiſe, nor upon any unlawfull termes, ſuch as wicked oaths, orders, degrees and ceremonies, neither Idolatrous places, nor yet in, nor amongſt the company of ſuch ungodly Docters, Batchelors, graduates, Maſters of Arts, Fellowes, Profeſſors nor Students, whoſe lives and converſations are in this Treatiſe deſcribed to be like <hi>Rome</hi> if not like <hi>Sodome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:48528:3"/>
And although theſe dayes be very hard and harſh unto many thouſands, as I and mine have had long and dolefull experience; yet in many reſpects, eſpecially of a hopefull plantation of Chriſts glorious Goſpell in the purity and authorithy thereof (for any other reformation can hardly or poſsibly be good) theſe dayes (I ſay) are far better then the former dayes, wherein we, and our predeceſſors went on ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, ſinne and ignorance, and when we would not commit ſinne enough, and that with greedineſſe, there were both wicked lawes and taske-maſters to urge us, as it was both in <hi>Egypt</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the dayes of <hi>Phraoh</hi> and <hi>Jeroboam;</hi> but praiſed be our good and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, that hath ſo mercifully and beyond both our expectation and deſerving infinite degrees, raiſed up the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> nation, both to breake all their bands, and cut their cords, yea, and to make ſuch a happy way for us, that both live and ſojourne here, whereby to eſcape the crafty ſnares of the bloody enemies, as a bird out of the hands of the fowler: Many Prophets and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous men in Chriſt, would have beene glad to ſee the dayes that we ſee, and could not ſee them, and to heare the things that we heare, but could not heare them.</p>
            <p>But leſt I be too tedious, I will not inſiſt by way of preamble, beeauſe few words are ſufficient for the wiſe, (I meane for the godly wiſe, and not thoſe mentioned, <hi>1 Cor. 1.18, 19.</hi>) I referre thee to this little portion of a worthy Martyrs obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (of never dying memory, notwithſtanding all the Clergies cruelty) who, when he was cloſe priſoner in the <hi>Fleet</hi> many yeeres, being not onely urged to write anum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of bookes againſt ambitious and covetous Clergie men, but to anſwer all their objections in many ſeverall diſputations and examinations, two of them being ſent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, two by the Biſhops to forge quarrels, and to try if they could entangle either him in ſpeech, or Maſter <hi>Greenwood,</hi> who was a cloſe priſoner alſo, and executed with him earely in a morning, before either any competent number of people gathered; or Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> heard (being twice reſcued by her before) whoſe ſeverall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminations, excellent obſervations, and their adverſaries calumniations, as alſo thoſe of that that other worthy martyr, Maſter <hi>Penry,</hi> are yet extant in print, though the light thereof bath beene long eclipſed and obſcured, with many other worthy mens Workes through the injury and iniquity of the times, untill now, that by Gods ſpeciall providence, undederſerved and unexpected love to us in Chriſt, that the ſtrong deludge of bookes which (hath been ſo long by ſuch wicked lawes, decrees and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions ſtopped, as that moſt ſevere booke of ſtatutes made in the Star Chamber againſt printers, and the cruelty uſed againſt <hi>John Lilbourne</hi> can teſtifie) doth (I ſay) overflow all the banks, both of helliſh and Romiſh limitation.</p>
            <p>All whoſe Workes, with learned Maſter <hi>Henry Ainſworths. Wilkinſons, Robinſons,</hi> with many others of the ſeparation, I wiſh thee to peruſe, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard them for thine owne good, as thou ſeeſt them tend to the glory of God, being tried by the touchſtone of his Word, and then, I hope, thou wilt give him the whole praiſe, and howſoever thou eſteems either of the Author or mee, his fraile inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I bid thee fare-well.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults eſcaped in the aforegoing page.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>In the preceding</hi> page, <hi>line 3. for believe, reade receive. and line 20. reade onely wiſe God.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48528:3"/>
            <head>The unlawfulneſſe of <hi>Vniverſity Learning,</hi> Or <hi>Sciences,</hi> falſly ſo called, extracted out of M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> HENRY BARROWS <hi>Booke.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>NE ſort of the Miniſtery of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is the <hi>Collegiat</hi> or <hi>idle</hi> Miniſtery, which may be divided, or rather diſtinguiſhed, becauſe ſometimes they are mixed and joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, one man being a Maſter of a <hi>College</hi> and a Deane, a Fellow of a Houſe, and a Preband, and each of them have a Parſonage or two for a need) into theſe two kindes, <hi>Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demicall</hi> and <hi>Cathedrall.</hi> The third ſort the <hi>Monaſticall,</hi> being by the hand of God and the Magiſtrates ſword cut off and ſuppreſſed. Theſe <hi>Academicall Divines</hi> live, have their education and degrees in the <hi>Colleges, Halls</hi> and <hi>Cells</hi> of the two <hi>Vniverſities.</hi> The originall corrupt cuſtomes and uſe of which places it is not my purpoſe here to diſcourſe; neither indeed have I skill aright to diſcuſſe whether, and how they ſprang from the <hi>Heathens,</hi> or from the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Only this I dare affirme, that from the Booke of God they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver derived theſe their <hi>Colleges, Schooles, Halls, Orders, Degrees, Vowes Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, Ceremonies, Attire,</hi> that I ſay not their <hi>Arts, Authours, exerciſe</hi> and <hi>uſe of their learnings, diſputations, commencements, &amp;c.</hi> But as they have received them elſewhere, ſo have they ever belonged to another head and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and can by no means (in this ſtate they now ſtand, and have time out of mind continued) be made to accord to the Goſpell and Kingdome of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whereof theſe <hi>Vniverſitie Divines</hi> have ever been the profeſſed and moſt bitter enemies, furniſhing <hi>Antichriſts</hi> Hoaſt in all the roomes and places even from the <hi>Popes</hi> chaire, to the Pariſh <hi>Prieſts</hi> pulpit or pue, with freſh ſervitors continually, corrupting the pure Fountaines, and perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the text it ſefe with their gloſſes, paraphraſes, notes, figures &amp;c. figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with their Schoole-learning, vaine arts, philoſophie, rethoricke, and logicke againſt the truth and ſervants of God, ſtriving hereby to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold <hi>Antichriſts</hi> ruinous kingdome and abominable wares, which theſe merchantmen ſet to ſaile for gaines as we by preſent experience ſee (now their portion and idle Monaſticall life, beginneth but even a little to be reproved by the light and power of the Goſpel) how theſe crafts-men, theſe <hi>Vniverſitie Clerks</hi> rage and take on, and with their Schoole-learning ſeeke to turne away the evident truth of God, to colour and plead for all the abomination and ſinne of the times, to heale the wound and uphold the throne of the Beaſt, to rend, reproach, and blaſpheme ſuch as ſpeake
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48528:4"/>and witneſſe againſt it, as their vituperous, unchriſtian and erroneous bookes which they daily publiſh, declare.</p>
            <p>Neither is their education and learning (if they be duely examined) ſuch as is required in the holy Miniſtery of <hi>Chriſt: All of them</hi> (as is ſaid) <hi>being nouriſhed even from their Cradles with the milke of ſuperſtition, inſtructed in the Schooles of heathen vanity, brought up in the Colleges of more then Monkiſh idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and diſorder, exerciſed in vaine and curious arts, whoſe divinity is by traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c.</hi> The truth of theſe things <hi>Mr. Giffard</hi> not being able to gainſay, ſeeketh to ſhuffle off with a bold boaſting challenge againſt men unto himſelfe unknowne upon the diſpence of bearing the ſhame, <hi>If he find not in the Vniverſities many Bachelours of Art for exceding in the knowledge of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall Arts, the three Tongues,</hi> Hebrew, Greek <hi>and</hi> Latin, <hi>or in ſound judgement of Divinity, even the Principall Maſters of</hi> Browniſme; <hi>which if it could in ſo few yeeres be obtained with more then Monkiſh idleneſſe, then may the</hi> Browniſts <hi>in ſome thing be believed.</hi> Firſt, we give him, to wit, that there are of thoſe he calleth <hi>Browniſts,</hi> ſundrie of greater continuance, and that have as high degree in thoſe Schooles with as high commendation as himſelfe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they boaſt not of ſuch things whereof they ought to be aſhamed. Then that there are, as many of his brethren the <hi>Monkes,</hi> that thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as skilfull as himſelfe, or the greateſt <hi>Clerke</hi> in the <hi>Vniverſity.</hi> But now, in all this, what will our ignorance helpe him or their ſtore of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſhew, that they have not been, and are not thus initiate and brought up. In their Grammer Schoole it cannot be denied, but they learned, and learne the <hi>Latin tongue,</hi> from the moſt heatheniſh and prophane authors, laſcivious <hi>Poets, &amp;c.</hi> which are allowed with the priviledge of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as moſt Chriſtian rudiments to be taught the youth in the publique Schoole. When they have paſſed all theſe formes, and can both ſay much of thoſe Authors by heart, and uſe their phraſe, then are they ſent to the <hi>Vniverſitie</hi> to learne the arts, and to be inſtructed in Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie, &amp;c. Hitherto it cannot be denied, but <hi>Heatheniſme,</hi> and ſuch exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable Idolatry as is found in thoſe Authors, is written and engraven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the tables of their heart, and filed upon their tongues; even from their infancie. Well and when they are come to the <hi>Vniverſitie,</hi> there are they firſt ſalted, as they call it in the <hi>Colledge,</hi> and matriculate in the publique Schooles ſolemnly ſworne upon the <hi>Proctors</hi> booke, to keepe their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſtatutes and ſecrets, and not to reveale her <hi>Myſteries,</hi> or teach her <hi>Arts</hi> any where but in the <hi>Vniverſitie.</hi> Then are they inſtructed both publique<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and privately in <hi>Logique</hi> and <hi>Retorick</hi> in the <hi>Elenches</hi> and <hi>Topicks,</hi> in the <hi>Tropes</hi> and <hi>Figures</hi> of all kindes; wherein they muſt be perfect, for theſe <hi>Arts</hi> are of ſpeciall uſe unto them and to ſerve at all aſſayes. Then proceed to <hi>Philoſophie,</hi> and there <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> amongſt them, out of whoſe mouth and writing they fetch their <hi>Poſitions and Axiomes; Definitions, Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſmes, Diſtinctions, &amp;c.</hi> out of his <hi>Ethicks, Oeconomicks and Politicks</hi> they fetch the order and government of their manners, private eſtates, and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48528:4"/>He yet further inſtructeth them of the <hi>Soule,</hi> and of the <hi>World,</hi> in large and ſpeciall bookes; of the heaven, of naturall and ſupernaturall things, of <hi>Nature, Fortune,</hi> the eternity of the <hi>world,</hi> and perpetuity of all creatures in their kind <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> of the regions of the ayr and ſeverall things in them contained, the Meteors, &amp;c. there learne they the cauſes of the Rainbow, the making of the winds, clouds, and of the whole skie, farre otherwiſe then is ſet downe in <hi>Geneſis.</hi> Yet leadeth he them higher, and ſheweth them the celeſtiall Spheares. Planers Stars, Quinteſſences, even from the Moone to their <hi>Caelum criſtallinum empiraeum,</hi> and their <hi>Primum Mobile,</hi> with their ſeverall places, dimenſurations, motions and <hi>Motors:</hi> yea, yet learne they more ſecret things with their conſtellations, radiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, influence, and predomination according to their ſignes, houſes, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, aſpects, eclipſes, &amp;c. whereby moſt ſtrange and wonderfull things are prognoſticate and foretold concerning the weather &amp; ſeaſons of the yeere the ſtate of Kingdomes, the diſeaſes and dangers to come, &amp;c. concerning nativities and times of death (commonly called <hi>Fortanes</hi>) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning things to come, or things paſt, ſtollen, loſt, found, &amp;c. Theſe things, it were frenſie, if not blaſphemy, to call vaine and curious Arts. Maſter <hi>Giffard</hi> would never beare it at the hands of ſuch blind <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> (whoſe bane ſuch deepe learning is) ſeeing theſe <hi>Sciences</hi> are vulgarly taught, ſtudied, practiſed, allowed and maintained, not onely in the <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities,</hi> but of the whole Church of <hi>England,</hi> as by their yeerly Prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations every where to be ſold, is to be ſeen. Theſe ſtudies and Arts we may not call <hi>perierga, curious,</hi> becauſe <hi>Mr. Giffard</hi> ſaith, <hi>Luke</hi> ſpeaketh onely of conjuration, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. But let him approve theſe lawfull by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and ſurely I will gladly confeſſe mine ignorance and ſin, in calling theſe ſtudies and Arts prophane, curious, unfit for a Chriſtian, much more for a Miniſter of the Church. Otherwiſe let not any through mine unskilfulneſſe (who peradventure repeate not aright, or in due place the termes of theſe Arts, as having either forgotten them through long diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, or it may be, never learned them a right) take occaſion either to carpe at me therefore, or eſpecially to thinke the better of theſe vaine and curious, yea, unlawfull and unchriſtian Arts and ſtudies, which have not onely no warrant in Gods Word, but are directly contrary unto, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly forbidden in the ſame, as were not hard to ſhew and prove, if the ſubject were not too large, and ſhould not make too wide a <hi>Parentheſis</hi> in this Treatiſe, and draw it out to a greater length then I would. I will not therefore ſtand here to diſcuſſe their philoſophicall problemes, paradoxes, axiomes, or ſeverall ſentences and opinions, which are authenticall and currant amongſt them, how evill they agree to the Word of God; or to ſhew how farre theſe curiors Inquiſitors, theſe Star-gazers, Aſtrologians, Calcars, Wizards Devines, exceed the bounds of faith and ſobrietiy, and paſſe the limits of Gods revealed Will: or, whether they may wander by theſe heatheniſh or divelliſh opinions of the Heavens, Stars, and their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutions,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48528:5"/>influence, &amp;c. <hi>Motors, Demones</hi> or <hi>Spirits,</hi> and how neere this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proacheth to conjuration: Or to ſhow how farre they are ſuffered to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, yea, profeſſe and practiſe in theſe divelliſh Arts: Let the bookes (that I charge no perſons) which are commonly bought and ſtudied in the <hi>Vniverſities,</hi> and in all other parts of the Realme without their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolement ſhew. Neither will I here proceed to repeat their other vaine, curious, fond, trifling and vile Arts and Studies, which were endleſſe. Only in this place I muſt here adde unto thoſe publike profeſſed Arts above recited, the ſtudy of all Heathen and prophane Hiſtories of all ages, nations, perſons wherein they muſt of neceſſity be prompt and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert; as from thoſe fountaines to draw their examples and platformes of manners and the government of States; as from whence to fetch the chiefe ornaments of their ſtile, Orations, Sermons, Bookes, to exemplyfie, illuſtrate, prove or improve: yea, as whereby to open and expound the Scriptures both of the old and new <hi>Teſtament,</hi> chiefly the old <hi>Prophets,</hi> without which they cannot be underſtood, but eſpecially <hi>Eſay</hi> and <hi>Daniel.</hi> As to <hi>Rethoricke</hi> and <hi>Logique</hi> they are ſo neceſſary, as without which it is impoſſible to underſtand or divide any part of the Scriptures aright; as without which they cannot underſtand or declare to the people by what <hi>trope</hi> or <hi>figure,</hi> by what <hi>form of argument</hi> or <hi>Syllogiſme</hi> the holy <hi>Ghoſt</hi> ſpeaketh.</p>
            <p>In theſe Arts and Studies, are the <hi>Academicall Divines,</hi> or rather <hi>Peripate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke Philoſophers,</hi> trained and exerciſed. In theſe they muſt needs ſpend ſeven of their firſt yeeres at the leaſt, elſe ſhould they be unfit to take thoſe degrees of <hi>Batchelor</hi> and <hi>Maſter of Art;</hi> or to make that publike profeſſion they doe of the Arts at their <hi>Commencements.</hi> In theſe Arts and Studies when they are once a little exerciſed and inſtructed, that they begin to perceive the grounds and method thereof, then are they trained both pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely and privately to defend or oppoſe againſt ſome of theſe <hi>Axiomes</hi> or <hi>Poſitions,</hi> both by way of Oration and Argument in their <hi>Sophiſmes</hi> and <hi>Diſputations,</hi> and therein all being approved (or at the leaſt allowed) they then take the firſt degrees of <hi>Schocles,</hi> and commence <hi>Bachellors</hi> of <hi>Art;</hi> and have as enſignes of their degree and knowledge, ſpeciall attire and furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture aſſigned them to be knowne from other common ſchollers; as the ſquare Cap, troncke Gowne, the Hood of one ſhoulder, the habite, &amp;c. which they muſt weare. Afteward having ſpent more then three yeeres in ſtudy on theſe Arts, and having done their publike acts <hi>Pro gradu,</hi> then they commence <hi>Maſters</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Arts,</hi> and are againe ſolemnly ſworne and made <hi>Regents</hi> and <hi>Lecturers</hi> of their Schooles, and ſit, reade, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute of the ſame Arts publikely in a ſolemne high Seat, Pulpit or Chaire for Orations; as alſo reade private Lectures thereof in their <hi>Colleges.</hi> Now I would here by the way know of Maſter <hi>Giffard,</hi> what time and leiſure a <hi>Bachelor</hi> of Art that continueth in the <hi>Vniverſitie,</hi> and proceedeth in thoſe orders and degrees can have, to ſtudy <hi>Divinity,</hi> or to grow ſo <hi>prompt</hi> in the knowledge, judgement, and exerciſe thereof, as he dare ingage his credit
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48528:5"/>he ſhall be found farre to paſſe therein ſuch as in therein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> been allowed publikely to preach, and of the Biſhops been made full <hi>Miniſters.</hi> But to our purpoſe, when theſe <hi>Clerkes</hi> are thus inſtituted and furniſhed with theſe liberall ſciences, and this ground-worke throughly laid, then may they in good time proceed to the ſtudy of <hi>Divinity,</hi> (as they call it) which is ſet out unto them in great volumes and infinite bookes of mens writings, both old and new, where they have ſuch variety of Paraphraſes, Commentaries, Common places, Catechiſes. &amp;c. (Not to trouble them at the firſt with the Primitive Hiſtories, Doctors, Councells) as they may in ſhort ſpace (if they ſtudy hard) become pretty Divines, and be able to ſhew their Authors judgement, yea (through the help of Roto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke and a good memory) to make a Sermon an houre long: Alwayes carefully provided that they utter no more, then that they have read in ſome allowed Author, having the privilege of the Church of <hi>England</hi> and preſume not either to underſtand the Text otherwiſe then their Authors interpret it, or to adde one note of their owne obſervation, for that (how conſonant ſoever to the truth) were great preſumption &amp; raſhneſſe. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may they over-far apply or inforce the judgement of their Authors againſt any preſent enormity eſtabliſhed by authority in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for that were intollerable againſt the peace of the Church, yea, ſeditious againſt the Magiſtrates authority, &amp;c. Thus, whileſt theſe <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines</hi> are held within theſe limits of modeſty and ſobriety, and continue with their Mother the <hi>Vniverſity,</hi> they may in due time ſet up their bills of challenge upon the Schoole doores that they meane to diſpute upon ſuch and ſuch queſtions of <hi>Divinity,</hi> and doe their acts <hi>pro gradu.</hi> Which being diſpatched, either <hi>in tenebris</hi> or in <hi>luce,</hi> then are they fit for the <hi>Commencement</hi> to be made <hi>Batchelors</hi> of <hi>Divinity.</hi> In like manner againſt that day muſt ſuch of them as have before paſſed all theſe degrees, and now are fit to proceed <hi>Doctors</hi> of <hi>Divinity,</hi> doe their acts in the publique Schoole accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly in theſe Divinity Diſputation Sermons <hi>ad derum, &amp;c.</hi> And againſt this ſolemne <hi>Commencement</hi> muſt eſpeciall choice be made of thoſe that are to commence <hi>Batchelors</hi> and <hi>Doctors</hi> of <hi>Divinity,</hi> to keepe the publique acts that day. And theſe for their further credits often times will under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to defend againſt all commers, ſuch <hi>Propoſitions</hi> as are moſt odious to all men, in whome is any light, conſcience, knowledge, or feare of God. As that it is lawfull for one man to have more Benefices and Flockes to attend on, then one at one time; That it is lawfull to be a <hi>Non reſident,</hi> to live from his flocke whereof hee taketh charge; That the unpreaching <hi>Miniſters</hi> are true and lawfull <hi>Paſtors,</hi> and the Sacraments by them delivered true and holy Sacraments; That <hi>Chriſts</hi> outward go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in his Church, practiſe and ſet downe by his Apoſtles, is not of neceſſity or perpetuall, but variable and arbitrable at the will of men, according to times eſtates &amp;c. Theſe and ſuch like, theſe <hi>Graduates</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and defend, the <hi>Vice-Chancelor</hi> and and whole <hi>Senate</hi> of the <hi>Vniverſity</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:48528:6"/>conclude and confirme, as Catholike <hi>Orthodox</hi> and moſt ſound, rejecting whatſoever Scriptures or Reaſons ſhall by theſe comicall Diſputers ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the <hi>Vniverſity Doctors</hi> and <hi>Divines,</hi> be brought againſt them. Well, unto this famous act are theſe <hi>Commencers</hi> ſolemnly brought in their ſeverall attires and arrayes, in their ſcarlet gownes, hoods, habits, caps, tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, &amp;c. with the <hi>Bedells</hi> proclaiming and carrying ſtaves and maces before them, with a great troupe of <hi>Graduates</hi> and <hi>Clerkes</hi> following them. And thus they march thorow the ſtreets to the place appointed and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for theſe prizes, where they have their ſticklers and moderators ready to reſcue, when they are in any diſtreſſe and where their adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries fight booty, being of their owne confederacie. Where it is not lawfull for any that will to oppoſe or to ſpeake for the truth of God. Neither are theſe queſtions diſcuſſed in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> tongue before thoſe multitude of people and ſtrangers, but in the <hi>Latine</hi> tongue after their <hi>Syllogiſticall</hi> and <hi>Romiſh</hi> manner leſt the folly of theſe <hi>Prophet</hi> ſhould be laid open unto all men, and theſe gameſters be hiſſed off the Stage by the people. Thus though with many other trifling ceremonies and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances then either I can, or care to recite, are theſe <hi>Academicall Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines,</hi> advanced to their degrees. Which <hi>degrees, titles, ceremonies, orders oathes vowes, manner of diſputations, &amp;c.</hi> how conſonant they are to the Miniſtry of <hi>Chriſt</hi> by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> rules, let Maſter <hi>Giffard</hi> or thoſe learned <hi>Divines</hi> approve by <hi>Chriſts</hi> Teſtament, as it ſtandeth them upon, that bring them in and exerciſe them in the Church. For our ſelves we proteſt we never there read or heard of any ſuch: and therefore cannot but thinke them fond ſtrange, and <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> ſuch as no way belong to or beſeeme the Miniſtry of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> neither are neceſſary or tolerable in <hi>Chriſts</hi> Church. Thus, even by this very brief and inſufficient recitall of but ſome of their Arts, ſtudies, orders, degrees &amp;c. I hope this aſſertion will not prove ſo falſe or incredible That the learned Miniſtry of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is nouriſhed even from their cradles with the make of ſuperſtition in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the Schooles of heathen vanity, brought up in the <hi>Collidges</hi> of more then <hi>Monkiſh</hi> idleneſſe and diſorder.</p>
            <p>For of ſuch kinde of Societies and Colledges of <hi>Miniſters</hi> and <hi>Clerks,</hi> to live together after this Monaſticall manner, we never read in the whole Booke of God. How like they are to the Schools of the <hi>Prophets</hi> at <hi>Naioth, Rama Iericho</hi> let their Arts ſtudies vowes cuſtomes, orders, ceremonies, degrees diſputations exerciſes &amp;c. declare. And as to the holy exerciſe of propheſie ſpoken of in the <hi>new Teſtament,</hi> it belonged unto and alwayes was exerciſed in ſome Chriſtian Congregation, in a more holy, reverent, and free manner, and not after thoſe Heatheniſh Popiſh cuſtomes above ſaid. We in <hi>Chriſts Teſtament</hi> never reade of ſuch a <hi>Monaſtical</hi> Miniſtry ſo withdrawne and ſequeſtred from any particular Congregation, Office, Charge and Function, as theſe <hi>Vniverſitie Divines</hi> and <hi>Miniſters</hi> are in their <hi>Colledges, Halls, Cells:</hi> Where they muſt needs live in idleneſſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48528:6"/>that are thus licentiate and diſſolute, that will beheld within no Chriſtian bonds or order. Wee never reade in <hi>Chriſts Teſtament</hi> of any ſuch Societies or Miniſters, that lived in no particular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, that were called to no particular Office, or Flocke, that live idlely, profeſſing to be Miniſters, and yet execute no certaine Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry or Function. When Maſter <hi>Giffard</hi> ſhall directly prove by the Scriptures theſe things to be lawfull, then ſo farre forth wee ſhall allow of theſe <hi>Vniverſitte Divines,</hi> theſe <hi>Collegiat Miniſters:</hi> And the rather, if hee alſo approve by Gods Word their worſhip in their <hi>Service-booke;</hi> and laſt of all (not to comber him with their manifold other ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous enſtomes, <hi>Commemoratons, &amp;c.</hi>) if hee can ſhew it to be lawfull for any <hi>Miniſter</hi> or Chriſtian to joyne unto and live in any ſuch <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Societie</hi> or <hi>Fellowſhip,</hi> where Gods holy Ordinance of honeſt mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage is by expreſſe law forbidden all the Fellowes and Schollers of theſe Colledges, they being no longer to remaine in that Societie, then they live unmarried, I ſay not now chaſtely: For how poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly or likely that is, for ſo many young men in the flower of their youth and prime of their ſtrength, eſpecially being noſeled in ſuch hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then vanity prophaneneſſe, vaine-glory, curioſitie, ſuperſtition, diſorder, diſſoluteneſſe, and (as is ſaid) contempt of Gods Ordinances, let any judge: yea, let the Scripture it ſelfe judge; where God ſheweth the reward of theſe ſinnes, how hee therefore giveth them up to the luſts of their owne hearts, unto uncleanneſſe, to ſhamefull luſts,<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> contrary to nature, to worke filthineſſe, and to diſhonour their owne bodies amongſt themſelves &amp;c. And ſo untill ſome of them can juſtifie this their life, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, cuſtome, vowes and proceedings of theſe <hi>Academicall Devines</hi> in their <hi>Schooles</hi> and <hi>Colledges,</hi> we muſt number and leave them with their brethren and ſiſters, the <hi>Monkes, Friers, Nuns, &amp;c.</hi> under Gods fearefull judgements, utterly in this eſtate unfit for the Miniſtrie or Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Yet would I not here, that any ſhould deeme or ſuppoſe that wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne any lawfull Arts or neceſſary Sciences, or any holy Exerciſes, or Schooles of inſtitution; and ſo doe labour to bring in barbariſme, as Maſter <hi>Giffard,</hi> Maſter <hi>Some,</hi> and others have given out. No, we are ſo far from it, as wee blame theſe <hi>Vniverſities, Colledges</hi> and <hi>Schooles,</hi> for their heathen, prophane, ſuperſtitious unchriſtian ſocieties diſorders, cuſtoms, ceremonies, for their vaine, curious, unlawfull Arts and ſtudies, and their manner of teaching and exerciſing them, &amp;c. We deſire with our whole hearts that the <hi>tongues</hi> and other godly <hi>Arts</hi> were taught not in the <hi>Vniverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> or a few places onely, but in all places where an eſtabliſhed Church is, at the leaſt in every City of the land. Yet this indeed we hold, That eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Chriſtian man ought to have his abiding and dwelling, and to bring up his children in ſome ſuch place where a Chriſtian Congregation is, and that all <hi>Schools</hi> of learning ought to be kept in ſuch places, where both <hi>Teachers</hi> and <hi>Schollers</hi> may be under the holy government and cenſures
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48528:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his Church, and may live and be kept in holy order. Then, that the Arts and Sciences which are thus taught or ſtudied, be not vaine, curious, or unlawfull but neceſſary and godly. Thirdly, that they be not taught, exerciſed or practiſed after any prophane, vain-glorious or ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious manner, but in all ſobriety, modeſty, and in the feare of God. To theſe few rules; if their <hi>Vniverſities, Colledges, Schooles,</hi> were reformed, then ſhould they not be as they now are, the <hi>Seminaries</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> the bane of the Church, the corruption of all youth in the Land: But then ſhould they be (that which they now pretend) the Schooles of all godly learning to garniſh the Church, to furniſh the Commonwealth with fit and vertuous men for every place, office, and eſtate.</p>
            <p>Here they will with one voyce anſwer, that the <hi>Vniverſities</hi> are the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries</hi> of Religon, of the Miniſtery of the land; the <hi>Schooles</hi> and <hi>Colledges</hi> of learning wherein the ſonnes of the <hi>Prophets</hi> are trained up as they were in <hi>Naioth,</hi> in <hi>Bethel Ieriche Ioruſalem</hi> and <hi>Corinth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the tree be knowne by the fruit, the Cockatrice by the poiſoned Egges the Viper by the ſpawne the neſt by the birds; then let the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Prieſts of the Land ſhew what kinde of <hi>Seminaries</hi> and <hi>Colledges</hi> theſe <hi>Vniverſities</hi> are. If theſe be the beſt fruit and famoufeſt men (that are inſtructed in nothing but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> corrupt and cavill againſt the truth) then let them take heed for the Axe is laid to the root of the tree, &amp;c. If alſo theſe your <hi>Vniverſities</hi> be compared to the Cities, whither theſe faithfull men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired (becauſe of theſe famous <hi>Prophets</hi>) to be inſtructed in the Lawes of God, we ſhall find them more like to the <hi>Sodomiticall Colledges</hi> and <hi>Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips</hi> of the Idolatrous <hi>Monks</hi> and <hi>Friors,</hi> brethren of a birth, even by both parents; then unto the holy aſſemblies of the <hi>Prophets.</hi> And this will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, if we compare them either in the perſons aſſembled, or in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and ends of their education and training.</p>
            <p>What the ſonnes of the <hi>Prophets</hi> were, is already ſhewed; namely, god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men that repaired to the Cities where theſe famous <hi>Prophets</hi> were moſt reſident, to be inſtructed in the Law of God. But the perſons that reſort to theſe <hi>Vniverſities</hi> are the children of all the prophane in the Land, that repaire thither to be inſtructed in heathen and vaine Arts, whereby they may get their living; or if they ſtudy <hi>Divinitie,</hi> (as they call it) they make an occupation, of it: It is but for their belly, for worldly promotion, and not for the glory of God, as the greedy ſeeking after their <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings by the one ſort, the ſelling of their cunning, and letting forth their tongues to hire of the other ſort, declareth.</p>
            <p>Third holy companies of <hi>Prophets</hi> mentioned in the Scriptures, were trained up in the Law of God, lived orderly in the feare of God together with their wives and families. But theſe <hi>Vnivenſity Colledges</hi> are a miſſe line rowte of very young men for the moſt part, and boyes together, lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their lives in Idolaity, confuſion; diſorder; ſpending their lives if vanity, folly, idleneſſe, living neither in the feare of God, not in an
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48528:7"/>well eſtabliſhed order of his Church, neither in any lawfull calling in the Common-wealth. They are forbidden in theſe ſocieties to live in holy wedlocke: If he be married, he may not there enter: If hee being entred marry, he may not there tarry. An endleſſe diſcourſe it were, but to recite their ſeverall Idolatrous prophane uſages myſteries, others, vows, ceremonies; all which evidently ſhew from whence they had their ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall, namely, from <hi>Antichriſts</hi> chaire, to which they have ever ſerved, and ſtill mall places do ſerve, fighting ſtoutly under his banner againſt the Faith and Church of Chriſt, ſupplying him continually with freſh ſoldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to carry abroad his merchandiſe, and fet abroach the deceits of <hi>Satan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither are they more like unto the Churches of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> then unto the Schooles of the <hi>Prophets:</hi> the Church of Chriſt is no cage of ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane and hatefull birds of their frie and off-ſpring: the Churches of Chriſt have no ſuch Colledges, Societies, Fellowſhips; the Churches of Chriſt have no ſuch heatheniſh and Idolatrous cuſtomes, excerciſes uſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, othes, vowes, ceremonies; they have no ſuch prophane Arts,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>&amp;</hi> 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 3.4.5 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Mat</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> vaine education and literature; they have no ſuch degrees and oſtentations of learning, neither are there found either <hi>Batchelors</hi> or <hi>Doctors</hi> of Divinity. Their <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Teachers</hi> are choſen for their knowledge, gravity, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life; they have no ſuch faſtuous and blaſphemous titles, but are called to a labour and a charge; for the faithfull performance where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, they rather deſire to be commended, then to be thus greeted in the Market-place. As they are by the Church wherein they ſerve, called to to this office; ſo are they orderly and reverently ordained by and in the ſame Congregation, with faſting and prayer, &amp;c. and not arrayed in ſearlet with the habit, hood, tippet, corner-cap, with their maces and beadles proclaiming before them, and ſuch a traine of the <hi>Popes</hi> Olerks, young and old following them through the ſtreets, till they march to the place where they play their prifes: Neither are they in this manner dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed <hi>Doctors</hi> by the delivering a booke unto them, ſworne upon a booke to their fathers fidelity, and their mothers myſteries adopted their ſonne by a ring and a kiſſe, or enthronized in a chaire, with many other ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and made <hi>Doctors</hi> of Divinity, <hi>Doctors</hi> in name and title onely,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any certaine office or Church wherein and whereunto to adminiſter.</p>
            <p>For this title of Divinity, I know not how to give it unto any mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man without blaſphemy, Chriſt onely excepted,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> in whom the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the God head dwelleth bodily.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> of Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Profeſſion of the Goſpell and faith of Chriſt, I can well away with and digeſt; but this <hi>Engliſh, Romiſh</hi> abſtract of Divinity, I am aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured came from the ſame forge that their title of the ſupreme Head of the Church did, and cannot with all the gloſſes, ſcholions, and learned interpretations they can deviſe, be made other then moſt high blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my againſt the ſacred perſon of <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> who is onely univerſall Doctor of all his Diſciples, and of all true Religion. And evill may <hi>D. S.</hi> either
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48528:8"/>defend or paterne his <hi>Doctorhood</hi> by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who in the ſame verſe, by him alledged, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.7. ſheweth a lawfull calling, a lawfull and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine office, and alſo a ſincere and faithfull adminiſtration thereof. But now, as Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Apoſtolique office is ceaſed, the Church being eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed and delivered to other certaine offices; ſo if <hi>Pauls</hi> Apoſtolique roome of <hi>Doctorſhip</hi> (as he calleth it) were void, I ſuppoſe, <hi>D. Some</hi> not the fitteſt man in the world for it; although (if it be as I heare) he can be no leſſe then an Apoſtle by his offices, hee being a <hi>Paſtor,</hi> if not a double or plurified <hi>Nonreſident Paſtor</hi> of many Churches; a <hi>Doctor</hi> you ſee by privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and ſtile, and a <hi>Deacon</hi> I meane alſo at <hi>Ely.</hi> And what was or could any Apoſtle be more? Yet, ſeeing all theſe are but forged ſtuffe, and that he hath neither any true office in the Church neither any true calling thereunto, &amp;c. we can take him but for a falſe Apoſtle at the beſt, if he ſit not in an <hi>Apoſtataes</hi> chaire, that I ſay not an <hi>Apoſtataes</hi> gowne ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where elſe, and ſo leave him either to repentance, or to follow his prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors to his appointed place.</p>
            <p>But by following this bird over farre, I had almoſt been trained from the neſt. I was ſhewing what little affinity there is betwixt the Churches of Chriſt, and theſe <hi>Vniverſities,</hi> theſe Colledges of Clerkes, theſe Schooles of <hi>Prophets.</hi> In the churches of Chriſt, the names and offices of <hi>Chancellor, Vice-chancellor, Commiſſary, Proctors, Taskers, Bedells, Provoſts, Maſters</hi> of <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, vice-Maſters, Bowcers, Deanes, Fellowes, &amp;c.</hi> are all ſtrange and unheard of; as alſo their ſeverall ſtatutes, cuſtomes, ceremonies their manner of degrees, and diſputing for their degrees and order of teaching, which were no ſmall labour but to reckon up.</p>
            <p>All which, as they are ſtrange to the Church of Chriſt, who find not in all Gods Word, any of theſe offices, degrees, ſtatutes, orders, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, ceremonies, vows &amp;c. neither any ſuch <hi>Vniverſities, colledges, Societies</hi> of Schollers; ſo (ſeeing they have no ground in the Word of God, no fellowſhip or communion with the Church) I ſee not why they ſhould have any more toleration then their elder brethren the <hi>Monks,</hi> who every way had as great ſhew of holineſſe and colour of utility to the Church as they, or theſe other <hi>Cathedrall Collegiate</hi> dens have, yea, and might both as ſoone and as well have beene purged of their <hi>Maſſe</hi> and <hi>Latine-ſervice,</hi> as theſe are: ſo that the ſame end that is beſalne the one remaineth the other. The Lord is not pleaſed with any voluntary Religion. That building that hath not the Word of God for the foundation, though it be dawbed with never ſo great cunning and learning,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and underſhored with never ſo great policy and power, though it be built as high as <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> yet ſhall it aſſuredly fall, and the greater ſhall be the fall thereof. As there is no building without the Word of God for the foundation; ſo is there no fellowſhip or communion out of the Church of God. And therefore no ſuch conſuſed <hi>Colledges,</hi> no ſuch Idolatrous aſſemblies as are not gathered unto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but unto <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> as live not in that Chriſtian
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48528:8"/>order and fellowſhip which <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath appointed to all his ſervants in his <hi>Church,</hi> but leade their lives in <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> diſorder, in <hi>Babyloniſh,</hi> if not <hi>Sodomitiſh</hi> confuſion; no ſuch heathen Schooles wherein youth is not trained up in the feare, knowledge and order of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but in vaine Arts,<note place="margin">Epheſ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Prov. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſuperſtition, Idolatry, diſorder, &amp;c. have any foundation in the Word of God, any fellowſhip with or allowance in the <hi>Church</hi> of God.</p>
            <p>But here will the <hi>Vniverſity</hi> Knights draw mee within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of theſe two abſurdities: Firſt, that I condemne all good Arts and Literature; then, that I quite drive them out of the world by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away the Schooles of the ſame, wherein youth might be trained and brought up.</p>
            <p>Nothing leſſe, I with my whole heart allow of any Art or Science that is conſonant to the Word of God, and to the Doctrine which is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to godlineſſe; onely the curious and heathen Arts prophane and vaine babblings and oppoſitions of Science falſly ſo called, which they profeſſe, and wherewith they poyſon and corrupt all the youth of the Land I abhorre, becauſe God condemnech.</p>
            <p>As ſor Schooles to teach the Tongues or any laudable or neceſſary Art, I wiſh them in abundance; that if it were poſſible, not onely the youth, but even the whole <hi>Church</hi> might be trained therein: I with my whole heart wiſh that all the Lords people were <hi>Prophets:</hi> ſuch an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my am I to the true knowledge and learning that I would not have it any longer kept ſecret in a myſterie, but even proclaimed upon the houſe top in every <hi>Cit,</hi> and in every ſtreet; yet ſtill and ever with this caution, that theſe Schooles both be in an eſtabliſhed <hi>Church</hi> (I meane in ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where the Saints live together in the faith order obedience and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of <hi>Chriſt</hi>) and not in ſuch Monkiſh, Idolatrous confuſed idle, prophane <hi>Colledges</hi> and <hi>Fellowſhips</hi> as theirs are: Likewiſe, that the <hi>Tongues</hi> or <hi>Sciences</hi> be here taught in an holy, ſanctified, reverend grave manner, and not in ſuch an unſanctified vaine manner as they uſe: So ſhall the earth be full of the knowledge of the Lord, as the waters that cover the ſea: for in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> are all his ſprings incloſed which by this meanes ſhould runne at every conduct and water the whole land abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, whereas now they lie in miſerable darkneſſe, wholly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>growne with brambles and briers.</p>
            <p>And ſurely, I even with marvell wonder, how theſe men can be ſo blinded to compare theſe wicked Idolatrous ſocieties, to the aſſemblies of the Prophets or unto the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> when you ſee they have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing common with them, or like unto them, either in the people aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, Doctrine taught, manner of teaching and learning, or order of life; when they utterly want warrant in the Word of God for ſuch kinde of <hi>Colledges, Societies</hi> and <hi>Schooles,</hi> theſe having beene derived either from the <hi>Heathens, Egyptians, Greekes, Perſians,</hi> that had their peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar <hi>Colledges</hi> and <hi>Schooles</hi> to their peculiar Sects, or elſe have iſſued
<pb facs="tcp:48528:9"/>out of the ſmoke of <hi>Antichriſts</hi> inventions out of the bottomleſſe pit. They alwayes have beene, and ſtill are the very hives and nurſeries of theſe armed poiſoned <hi>Locuſts</hi> and venomous <hi>Scorpions,</hi> I meane, either that falſe Miniſtery of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> even all the governing and teaching <hi>Prieſts</hi> as <hi>Cardinalls, Archbiſhop. Biſh. Suffraganes, Archdeacons, Chancellors, Commiſſaries, Civill Doctors, Advocates, Proctors, Vagrant,</hi> roving <hi>Miniſters and Preachers, pariſh Prieſts, &amp;c.</hi> or thoſe counterfeit religious hypocrites, Monks, Friers, Nuns, Clerkes, or (as we now of late call them) Schollers. All which have in innumerable multitudes from time to time, and at all times ſwarmed and iſſued out of theſe hives into the face of the whole earth, corrupting and deſtroying every greene thing, poyſoning the pure foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raines of Gods Word with their accurſed gloſſes, deepe learning, ſubtill and figurative interpretations, darkning the ſunne and infecting the ayre therewith; as alſo with the blaſphemous traditions of their King <hi>Apolluon</hi> that Angell of the bottomeleſſe pit. They have alwayes moſt peſtilently fought under this their Captaine againſt the Lambe, his Goſpell and Church, plentifully furniſhing and continually ſupplying all the offices and roomes belonging to that huge <hi>Midianitiſh</hi> Hoſt of <hi>Antichriſt:</hi> the Leaders, Captaines, and Officers whereof, are, and ever have beene, wholly taken out of theſe <hi>Seraliaes;</hi> even from the <hi>Popes</hi> perſon to the loweſt <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How they are reformed by having this <hi>Engliſh</hi> porteſſe their ſervice-booke in ſtead of their old maſſe-booke, may partly by that which is above written concerning the ſame, appeare: but more manifeſtly, by taking a view of fome of the blaſphemous Idolatrous cuſtomes which ſtill remaine in practiſe with them in the ſame manner, as they did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Pope:</hi> all or any of which it is not here my purpoſe any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to deſcribe. It ſufficeth me to have ſhewed them to be confuſed, Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous, unchriſtian, unlawfull aſſemblies and ſocieties; ſo farre from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be compared unto, or juſtified by the aſſemblies of the Prophets or that heavenly exerciſe of propheſie now in the Church of Chriſt, as they are not to be ſuffered in a Chriſtian Common-wealth. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore here againe once more I conlude, that both theſe ungodly aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, as alſo the Cathedrall Dennes and Colledges, ought by as good right to be aboliſhed, as their other brethen and ſiſters of a birth, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries and Nunneries are, ſeeing they all want foundation in the Word, had one and the ſame helliſh originall, had and theſe ſtill retaine the ſame blaſphemous incurable abuſes, which can by no way be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed but by their utter diſſolution.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:48528:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PROTESTANTS ACCOUNT Of His Orthodox Holding in Matters of Religion, at this preſent in difference in the CHURCH: <hi>For his own and others better confirmation or rectification in the points treated on,</hi> Humbly ſubmitted to the cenſure of the Church of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed by ROGER DANIEL, Printer to the Univerſitie of <hi>Cambridge.</hi> 1642.</p>
            <p>And are to be ſold by <hi>John Milleſon,</hi> Stationer over againſt great <hi>St. Maries</hi> in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
